<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>user &#8211; BBC Online Mills</title>
	<atom:link href="https://bbc.online.mills.edu/author/user/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://bbc.online.mills.edu</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 14:59:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Boris Johnson deliberately misled parliament: Report</title>
		<link>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/boris-johnson-deliberately-misled-parliament-report/</link>
					<comments>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/boris-johnson-deliberately-misled-parliament-report/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[user]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 14:59:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://bbc.online.mills.edu/?p=22</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Boris Johnson deliberately misled the British parliament in an unprecedented way over rule-breaking parties at his office during Covid-19 lockdowns, a committee said on Thursday in a damning verdict that further tarnished the former prime minister Almost a year ago, Johnson was talking about remaining prime minister into the 2030s. But the privileges committee &#8211; ... <a title="Boris Johnson deliberately misled parliament: Report" class="read-more" href="https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/boris-johnson-deliberately-misled-parliament-report/" aria-label="More on Boris Johnson deliberately misled parliament: Report">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Boris Johnson deliberately misled the British parliament in an unprecedented way over rule-breaking parties at his office during Covid-19 lockdowns, a committee said on Thursday in a damning verdict that further tarnished the former prime minister</p>
<p>Almost a year ago, Johnson was talking about remaining prime minister into the 2030s. But the privileges committee &#8211; the main disciplinary body for lawmakers &#8211; said on Thursday he should now be stripped of having automatic access to parliament.</p>
<p>The committee also accused Johnson of being &#8220;complicit in a campaign of abuse and attempted intimidation&#8221; towards them.</p>
<p>In typically combative style Johnson, who in 2019 led the Conservatives to a landslide election victory, dismissed the report as &#8220;a lie&#8221; and &#8220;a charade&#8221;, and accused committee members of waging a vendetta against him.</p>
<p>The stand-off will do little to heal the deep divisions in the Conservatives and can only pile pressure on Prime Minister Rishi Sunak, whose push to try to boost Britain&#8217;s flagging economy is being overshadowed by the ongoing Johnson drama.</p>
<p>The more than 100-page report detailed six events held at Downing Street, the prime minister&#8217;s offices and residence.</p>
<p>&#8220;We conclude that in deliberately misleading the House Mr Johnson committed a serious contempt,&#8221; the committee said:</p>
<p>&#8220;The contempt was all the more serious because it was committed by the prime minister, the most senior member of the government. There is no precedent for a prime minister having been found to have deliberately misled the House (of Commons, lower house of parliament).&#8221;</p>
<div id="beb218cc-9b85-4485-8140-a38b0f80797a">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>It recommended that he should not be entitled to a former member&#8217;s pass, which enables most former prime ministers and lawmakers to gain automatic access to parliament. Parliament will consider the committee&#8217;s recommendation on Monday.</p>
<p>Asked about the report&#8217;s conclusions, a spokesman for Sunak said the prime minister had not as yet read it but he believed the committee had carried out the inquiry properly and &#8220;that it would not be right to traduce or criticise the work&#8221; of it.</p>
<p>The committee, made up of four Conservatives and three opposition lawmakers, rejected Johnson&#8217;s defence that the gatherings were within the rules and that his advisers had supported his belief that was the case.</p>
<p>Instead, it said, Johnson was &#8220;deliberately disingenuous when he tried to reinterpret his statements to the House to avoid their plain meaning and reframe the clear impression that he intended to give&#8221;.</p>
<p>It said that were Johnson still a member of parliament, it would have recommended a suspension from the House of Commons for 90 days.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="d69f8573-67f6-49b6-a888-42f6502bbd97">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-title">
<h2>Daming</h2>
</div>
</div>
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>Johnson resigned from parliament last week after seeing an advance copy of the report, calling the inquiry a &#8220;witch hunt&#8221;, a criticism he made again after its publication.</p>
<p>&#8220;I believed, correctly, that these events were reasonably necessary for work purposes. We were managing a pandemic,&#8221; he said in a statement.</p>
<p>He said the report marked a &#8220;dreadful day&#8221; for members of parliament (MPs) and for democracy. &#8220;This decision means that no MP is free from vendetta, or expulsion on trumped up charges by a tiny minority who want to see him or her gone from the Commons,&#8221; he said.</p>
<p>He accused the committee of using mystical powers to see things that he had not seen at Downing Street, when, he said, he was duty bound to thank staff who were departing or for their work on Covid-19. The committee did not accept his defence.</p>
<p>The Labour Party said the report was &#8220;damning&#8221;.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="92788ed9-bca3-4866-adce-ded9710a170c">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>&#8220;While Rishi Sunak is distracted with the ongoing Tory soap opera people are crying out for leadership on the issues that matter to them,&#8221; said Thangam Debbonaire, a member of Labour&#8217;s top team.</p>
<p>A former Johnson aide said the report did little more than confirm his &#8220;semi-retirement&#8221; from where he would still exert &#8220;huge influence&#8221; over the Conservative Party.</p>
<p>Johnson has apologised for his conduct but repeatedly denied deliberately misleading parliament, saying he took advice from his aides that his office were following the rules.</p>
<p>But so-called Partygate spelt the beginning of the end for his tenure as prime minister. A rebellion in the Conservative Party last year, when ministers resigned en masse, forced him in July to say he would step down. He left office in September.</p>
<p>He resigned from parliament last week, ending his time as a so-called backbench lawmaker who continued to wield significant influence within the Conservatives that at times undermined Sunak&#8217;s authority.</p>
<p>They have also rowed this week over the former prime minister&#8217;s resignation honours list.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/boris-johnson-deliberately-misled-parliament-report/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How migrant tragedy unfolded on the high seas off Greece</title>
		<link>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/how-migrant-tragedy-unfolded-on-the-high-seas-off-greece/</link>
					<comments>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/how-migrant-tragedy-unfolded-on-the-high-seas-off-greece/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[user]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 14:58:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://bbc.online.mills.edu/?p=19</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Greece confronts its worst sea disaster in years, questions are mounting about how potentially hundreds of migrants drowned even as their vessel was being shadowed by the Greek coastguard. At least 78 people died when the fishing vessel flipped and capsized in international waters south-west of Greece early on Wednesday. Authorities rescued 104 people ... <a title="How migrant tragedy unfolded on the high seas off Greece" class="read-more" href="https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/how-migrant-tragedy-unfolded-on-the-high-seas-off-greece/" aria-label="More on How migrant tragedy unfolded on the high seas off Greece">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Greece confronts its worst sea disaster in years, questions are mounting about how potentially hundreds of migrants drowned even as their vessel was being shadowed by the Greek coastguard.</p>
<p>At least 78 people died when the fishing vessel flipped and capsized in international waters south-west of Greece early on Wednesday. Authorities rescued 104 people but hundreds are feared missing, with some witnesses saying up to 750 people were aboard.</p>
<p>According to timelines from authorities and activists, the Greek coastguard was alerted to the presence of the vessel 47 nautical miles (87 km) south west of Greece at around 0800 GMT on 13 June. It capsized at around 2300 GMT that day.</p>
<p>Exactly what happened in the intervening 15 hours remains unclear. A migrant charity says a person they were in contact with on the boat said it was in distress, but Greek authorities say it repeatedly refused offers of help.</p>
<p>Following are some details from the accounts so far:</p>
<p><strong>Leaving Libya</strong></p>
<p>Two Greek sources familiar with police inquiries say that, based on accounts from about 30 survivors, the ageing fishing vessel left Tobruk, in Libya, early on 10 June.</p>
<p>Passengers paid $4,500 for passage to Italy, the two Greek sources said. Based on some accounts, there were about 20 women and children among the passengers. They booked their voyage on social media, according to a maritime ministry official.</p>
<p>Traffickers had promised ample room on the vessel, but once passengers arrived at the scheduled departure point and saw it was overcrowded it was impossible to turn back, those sources said.</p>
<div id="88530a01-a58e-432d-b543-ad0de961018e">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>Over the next few days at sea the boat developed “two or three” mechanical faults, which were fixed by a crew of between 8-10 people. Progress was slow.</p>
<p>“If people reacted the traffickers would shout and threaten to stop giving them water,” one of the sources said, citing accounts of survivors.</p>
<p>Passengers were also adamant about getting to Italy, which borders visa-free EU member states permitting safe passage, rather than Greece, circled by Balkan states that are taking an increasingly tough line on migration, they said.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="a47d0713-a4b9-4be8-9592-42f643b67bb3">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p><strong>Mixed Messages</strong></p>
<p>Advocacy group Alarm Phone, which operates a trans-European network supporting rescue operations, said it received its first call from the boat just after 1200 GMT on 13 June to say the vessel was in distress. The person they communicated with said “they cannot survive the night”.</p>
<p>Greek authorities had also established contact with the vessel.</p>
<p>But in repeated communication with the boat, from 1330 to 1800 GMT Greek authorities say people on the vessel told them they wanted to sail to Italy and wanted no assistance from Greece.</p>
<p>Aerial photos of the vessel taken by the Greek coastguard hours before the tragedy unfolded showed a vessel crammed with people on its exposed decks. Some had their hands outstretched.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="994246b6-f57d-45c6-9b27-47abc7d76b8b">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>Greek officials say they were faced with a dilemma on what to do with a vessel that had repeatedly declined offers of assistance, worried that even the slightest shift could unbalance the boat.</p>
<p>“You cannot carry out a violent diversion on such a vessel with so many people on board, without them wanting to, without any sort of cooperation,” said Nikos Alexiou, a spokesperson for Greece’s coastguard.</p>
<p>Under EU law, determining whether a vessel is in distress is based on a number of factors, including the state of the vessel, the number of people on board, weather conditions and availability of safety, navigation and communication equipment.</p>
<p>Adriana Tidona, researcher on migration at Amnesty International, said the organisation was deeply concerned at lack of clarity from Greece over the incident.</p>
<p>“The Greek government had specific responsibilities toward every passenger on the vessel, which was clearly in distress,” Tidona said.</p>
<p>When the boat reported engine failure and stalled, a coastguard vessel shadowing them came closer. In just under 25 minutes, coastguard witnesses saw the boat tilt sharply right to left. In 10 to 15 minutes, the boat was gone.</p>
<p>The precise number of victims might never be known. The waters in which the boat sank are some of the deepest in the Mediterranean, where depths can exceed 5 km.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/how-migrant-tragedy-unfolded-on-the-high-seas-off-greece/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tropical Cyclone Biparjoy: Power disrupted, heavy rains lash India, Pakistan</title>
		<link>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/tropical-cyclone-biparjoy-power-disrupted-heavy-rains-lash-india-pakistan/</link>
					<comments>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/tropical-cyclone-biparjoy-power-disrupted-heavy-rains-lash-india-pakistan/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[user]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2023 14:57:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://bbc.online.mills.edu/?p=16</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Roofs were blown off houses and trees and electric poles uprooted, leaving thousands without power as a severe cyclone made landfall and rain lashed both the Indian and Pakistani coasts early on Friday. At least two people died in India&#8217;s western state of Gujarat after being swept away by flood waters just before the cyclone ... <a title="Tropical Cyclone Biparjoy: Power disrupted, heavy rains lash India, Pakistan" class="read-more" href="https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/tropical-cyclone-biparjoy-power-disrupted-heavy-rains-lash-india-pakistan/" aria-label="More on Tropical Cyclone Biparjoy: Power disrupted, heavy rains lash India, Pakistan">Read more</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Roofs were blown off houses and trees and electric poles uprooted, leaving thousands without power as a severe cyclone made landfall and rain lashed both the Indian and Pakistani coasts early on Friday.</p>
<p>At least two people died in India&#8217;s western state of Gujarat after being swept away by flood waters just before the cyclone hit.</p>
<p>More than 180,000 people were evacuated in India and Pakistan in the last few days as authorities braced for the cyclone, named Biparjoy, which means &#8216;disaster&#8217; or &#8216;calamity&#8217; in the Bengali language.</p>
<p>It made landfall late on Thursday near Jakhau, a port in Gujarat that is close to the border with Pakistan, weather officials said.</p>
<p>Biparjoy had weakened to a cyclonic storm from a severe cyclonic storm on Friday morning, India&#8217;s Metereological Department said in its latest bulletin, with speeds going down from 105 km (65.24 miles) to 85 km (52.82 miles). Wind speeds are likely to reduce further by afternoon, the bulletin said.</p>
<p>Two men, both shepherds, died while trying to rescue their cattle from being swept away during heavy rains and floods in Gujarat&#8217;s Bhavnagar district on Thursday evening, the cyclone control room said.</p>
<div id="c0a4ee5a-32a1-4dac-b504-c485479eefec">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>Power was disrupted at many places in the Kutch district of Gujarat because of strong winds, said Amit Arora, a top district official overseeing rescue operations.</p>
<p>In neighbouring Pakistan, the cyclone had no major impact, with rain reported in some parts of the southern metropolis of Karachi, which was on high alert.</p>
<p>Pakistan&#8217;s weather department advised local authorities to remain on alert for expected heavy rain in some coastal areas until Saturday.</p>
<p>Gale-force winds caused hundreds of trees to be uprooted in the coastal areas of Gujarat, and heavy rains led to electricity poles being damaged, causing thousands to be without power on Friday, local officials said.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="9aab44fe-2c11-4823-96f5-8f383c4a1c6d">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>India&#8217;s weather department warned of heavy to very heavy rainfall in Gujarat and the neighbouring state of Rajasthan through Friday. Pakistan&#8217;s weather department said moderate to heavy rain was expected in the Hyderabad, Nooriabad and Thatta regions.</p>
<p>Biparjoy weakened after hitting land with a wind speed of 85 km per hour (53 miles per hour) to 115 kmph (71 mph) Mrutyunjay Mohapatra, director general at the India Meteorological Department said earlier on Friday.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="e6cff9e2-1751-4faf-b31b-0fe3a6b41290">
<div class="storyCard eyOoS qwBlA">
<div class="   
                  story-element"></p>
<div class="story-element story-element-text">
<div>
<p>Local television showed visuals of uprooted trees, people sheltering against strong winds and debris lying on roads in the aftermath of the cyclone.</p>
<p>Biparjoy was classified as a category one storm, the least severe on a scale of one to five.</p>
<p>The government had directed all offshore oil installations to ensure the immediate return of all staff to land and advised ports to also take preventive action, but there was no word on how the landfall had affected operations, if at all.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://bbc.online.mills.edu/2023/06/17/tropical-cyclone-biparjoy-power-disrupted-heavy-rains-lash-india-pakistan/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
